{"tossups":[{"question":"This author worked in the “laboratory of vocabulary” to “extract a radium of the word,” according to a poem by Mina Loy. This author’s essay “Miss Furr and Miss Skeene” may be the first literary work to explicitly use the word “gay” to refer to a same-sex relationship. This author’s series of “word portraits” includes one titled “Ada,” which was inspired by the (*) San Francisco-born lover who lived with this author at 27 rue de Fleurus [roo duh fluh-ROOSE]. This author’s thousand-page novel about the Hersland and Dehning families exemplifies her technique of repeating everyday words ad nauseam. This author of The Making of Americans coined the phrase “Lost Generation.” For 10 points, the phrase “there is no there there” was coined by what author of The Autobiography of Alice B. Toklas?","formatted_answer":"Gertrude <b><u>Stein<\/b><\/u>","answer":"Gertrude <b><u>Stein<\/b><\/u>","category":"Fine Arts","subcategory":"Visual Fine Arts","packetNumber":4,"questionNumber":1},{"question":"According to Patrick McGilligan, a usage of this word that one man dismissed as a “dollar-book Freudian gag” was inspired by the name of the horse that won the 1914 Kentucky Derby. That usage of this word was parodied less than eight months later in a gag from the film Hellzapoppin’. In The Sims, this word and the word “kaching” are cheat codes that give the player a thousand simoleons. In a scene from The (*) Critic, a filmmaker says this word in closeup before a medium shot reveals that he’s advertising frozen peas. The News on the March reporter Jerry Thompson is tasked with finding the meaning of this word in a film whose final scene shows a furnace at Xanadu where a sled with this word on it is being burned.. For 10 points, name this dying word of Kane in Citizen Kane.","formatted_answer":"<b><u>rosebud<\/b><\/u>","answer":"<b><u>rosebud<\/b><\/u>","category":"Fine Arts","subcategory":"Other Fine Arts","packetNumber":4,"questionNumber":2},{"question":"Mel Blanc delivered the words “Froot Loops” in this unusual manner as the original voice actor for Toucan Sam. The jazz singer born Anita Belle Colton derived her stage name in this manner from a word meaning “money.” In the film Gold Diggers of 1933, Ginger Rogers sings a verse of “We’re in the Money” in this unusual manner. In Louis Sachar’s Holes, Rex Washburn’s (*) nickname is derived in this manner. A slur meaning “white person” is dubiously speculated to come from a West African language or to have been derived in this manner from the word “foe.” This system is the most familiar English analogue of verlan [vair-LAHN], a French-language argot. For 10 points, what language game is the origin of the words “amscray” and “ixnay”?","formatted_answer":"<b><u>Pig Latin<\/b><\/u> (The jazz singer is Anita O’Day, and Rex’s nickname in Holes is X-Ray.)","answer":"<b><u>Pig Latin<\/b><\/u> (The jazz singer is Anita O’Day, and Rex’s nickname in Holes is X-Ray.)","category":"Literature","subcategory":"American Literature","packetNumber":4,"questionNumber":3},{"question":"This word is sung after the line “you are a killer” at the end of the medley that opens Nina Simone’s album Emergency Ward, in which this word is used as a refrain. In Gregorian chant, the last syllable of this word was traditionally sung with a long melisma. The prosody of this word inspired the rhythm of a John Adams piece for two pianos titled for a (*) junction of this name. The chord progression “F major, G major, A minor, F major” mirrors the contents of the lyrics being sung in a song of this title from Various Positions. Repeated exclamations of this word are interrupted by the line “for the Lord God Omnipotent reigneth” in a scene from a 1741 oratorio. For 10 points, name this word which is repeated in the chorus that concludes Part II of Handel’s Messiah.","formatted_answer":"<b><u>hallelujah<\/b><\/u> [or <b><u>alleluia<\/b><\/u>; accept <b><u>Hallelujah<\/b><\/u> Junction; accept “<b><u>Hallelujah<\/b><\/u> Chorus”] (The Nina Simone medley includes a cover of George Harrison’s “My Sweet Lord.”)","answer":"<b><u>hallelujah<\/b><\/u> [or <b><u>alleluia<\/b><\/u>; accept <b><u>Hallelujah<\/b><\/u> Junction; accept “<b><u>Hallelujah<\/b><\/u> Chorus”] (The Nina Simone medley includes a cover of George Harrison’s “My Sweet Lord.”)","category":"Fine Arts","subcategory":"Auditory Fine Arts","packetNumber":4,"questionNumber":4},{"question":"Dennis Baron’s history of these words notes that one of them was first used in the romance William and the Werewolf. Some of these words are named after the author of A Comprehensive Introduction to Differential Geometry, Michael Spivak. In 1884, the composer Charles Crozat Converse coined one of these words, spelled “t-h-o-n.” A preschool in Sweden called (*) Egalia gained fame for its use of hen, which is an example of the “epicene” [EP-uh-seen] type of these words. Brigitte Macron was among the politicians who criticized the 2021 addition of one of these words to the Petit Robert [puh-TEE roh-BAIR] French dictionary. Neologistic examples of these words in English include “fae” [fay] and “ze” [zee]. For 10 points, name this part of speech exemplified by the gender-neutral “they.”","formatted_answer":"gender-neutral (third person singular) <b><u>pronoun<\/b><\/u>s [or epicene <b><u>pronoun<\/b><\/u>s; or neo<b><u>pronoun<\/b><\/u>s]","answer":"gender-neutral (third person singular) <b><u>pronoun<\/b><\/u>s [or epicene <b><u>pronoun<\/b><\/u>s; or neo<b><u>pronoun<\/b><\/u>s]","category":"Fine Arts","subcategory":"Auditory Fine Arts","packetNumber":4,"questionNumber":5},{"question":"The Etymologicum Magnum says that this character’s name derives from the fact that his mother gave birth to him on the road in the rain. Some characters refer to this man using the two-word phrase me tis [meh teece], which resembles the single word mêtis [MEH-teece] that forms part of one of this man’s epithets. In one story, this character’s name was chosen by his grandfather, and comes from a verb meaning something like “to be (*) hated.” Phrases like “a man of many devices” and “a complicated man” have been used to translate the word polytropos [poh-loo-troh-pohss] describing this man. Some writers link the Latin version of this character’s name to a word meaning “scar,” in reference to the scar which Eurycleia [YOO-ruh-CLAY-uh] recognizes him by. For 10 points, name this title character of an epic by Homer.","formatted_answer":"<b><u>Odysseus<\/b><\/u> [or <b><u>Ulysses<\/b><\/u>] (In the story of Polyphemus, both ou tis and me tis are used to refer to Odysseus after he introduces himself as Outis, or “no man.”)","answer":"<b><u>Odysseus<\/b><\/u> [or <b><u>Ulysses<\/b><\/u>] (In the story of Polyphemus, both ou tis and me tis are used to refer to Odysseus after he introduces himself as Outis, or “no man.”)","category":"Fine Arts","subcategory":"Auditory Fine Arts","packetNumber":4,"questionNumber":6},{"question":"Cornelius Castoriadis [caster-ee-AD-iss] unusually used this word as a count noun to refer to indeterminate beings, as opposed to determinate beings called “ensembles.” In abstract algebra, either this word or “groupoid” is used to refer to a set equipped with a single binary operation. A progressive rock band with this name is led by Christian Vander, who invented the (*) Kobaïan [koh-BYE-in] language for the band’s lyrics. This word, which comes from the Greek for a thick oozing ointment, is followed by the letters “t-i-s-m” in the name of a process that is common at mid-ocean ridges. The adjectival form of this word is rarely used as a synonym of “igneous.” For 10 points, name this word for molten material that is extruded as lava.","formatted_answer":"<b><u>magma<\/b><\/u>","answer":"<b><u>magma<\/b><\/u>","category":"Science","subcategory":"Other Science","packetNumber":4,"questionNumber":7},{"question":"In 1922, Cyril Turner wrote the phrase “Vanderbilt 7200” in this location, prompting a flood of phone calls to the hotel where he was staying. After abandoning the pseudonym Alberto Ruiz-Tagle, the nationalist Carlos Wieder starts writing words in this location in Roberto Bolaño’s [boh-LAWN-yoh’s] Distant Star. In another novel, Mrs. Coates and Mrs. Bletchley think that they see the words (*) “Glaxo” and “Kreemo” written in this location. Onlookers speculate about the words being written in this location before realizing that they are an advertisement for toffee in a scene from Mrs Dalloway. Words can be written in this location using a combination of paraffin oil and exhaust, which creates white smoke. For 10 points, name this location where messages can be written by skilled pilots.","formatted_answer":"the <b><u>sky<\/b><\/u> [or the <b><u>air<\/b><\/u>; accept <b><u>sky<\/b><\/u>-writing]","answer":"the <b><u>sky<\/b><\/u> [or the <b><u>air<\/b><\/u>; accept <b><u>sky<\/b><\/u>-writing]","category":"Literature","subcategory":"British Literature","packetNumber":4,"questionNumber":8},{"question":"Judy Grahn’s theory that a certain slur derives from this person’s name is mentioned in an Antonia Fraser book that uses different spellings of this person’s name to refer to the historical and legendary aspects of this person’s legacy. A spelling that adds an “n” to this person’s name comes from an account in which this person releases a hare that is interpreted as a good omen, written by (*) Cassius Dio. This person’s popularity as a patriotic symbol in Victorian Britain was influenced by the theory that her name comes from a root meaning “victory” in Celtic. Tacitus erroneously added an extra “c” to the name of this wife of Prasutagus. For 10 points, name this queen of the Iceni [eye-SEEN-eye] who led an uprising against the Romans in Britain.","formatted_answer":"<b><u>Boudicca<\/b><\/u> [or <b><u>Boadicea<\/b><\/u> or <b><u>Bonduca<\/b><\/u> or <b><u>Boudicea<\/b><\/u> or <b><u>Buddug<\/b><\/u>] (The Fraser book is The Warrior Queens.)","answer":"<b><u>Boudicca<\/b><\/u> [or <b><u>Boadicea<\/b><\/u> or <b><u>Bonduca<\/b><\/u> or <b><u>Boudicea<\/b><\/u> or <b><u>Buddug<\/b><\/u>] (The Fraser book is The Warrior Queens.)","category":"History","subcategory":"Ancient History","packetNumber":4,"questionNumber":9},{"question":"The word for “transom window” in one of these two Indo-European languages is borrowed from a phrase meaning “What is that?” in the other language. Removing the initial “c” and “a” from a slang word in one of these languages produced a derogatory term for speakers of the other language. [Read the following sentence slowly:] The word “loanword” is a calque [calk] from one of these languages, and the word “calque” is a (*) loanword from the other. The results of a war between countries speaking these two languages inspired the coining of the word “revanchism” [ruh-VONCH-ism]. The Emcee greets audience members in English and these two languages in the opening number of the musical Cabaret. For 10 points, name these languages that call each other allemand [all-MAHN] and Französisch [frahnt-SUH-zish].","formatted_answer":"<b><u>French<\/b><\/u> and <b><u>German<\/b><\/u> [accept <b><u>français<\/b><\/u> for “French” and <b><u>Deutsch<\/b><\/u> for “German”] (The French word for a transom window is vasistás, borrowed from the German was ist das. The derogatory term boche derives from the French caboche.)","answer":"<b><u>French<\/b><\/u> and <b><u>German<\/b><\/u> [accept <b><u>français<\/b><\/u> for “French” and <b><u>Deutsch<\/b><\/u> for “German”] (The French word for a transom window is vasistás, borrowed from the German was ist das. The derogatory term boche derives from the French caboche.)","category":"Literature","subcategory":"British Literature","packetNumber":4,"questionNumber":10},{"question":"The 2011 update of Alex P. Schmid’s “academic consensus definition” of this word includes twelve elements. A certification from the Secretary of the Treasury is part of the definition of this word given in a “Risk Insurance Act” that provides a federal backstop for some insurance claims. A proposed U.N. “comprehensive convention” on this phenomenon has been deadlocked since (*) 1997 because of a failure to agree on the definition of this word. The U.S. Code’s definition of this word requires that it involve “subnational groups” or “clandestine agents.” The difficulty of defining this word is summarized by the adage “One man’s [blank] is another man’s freedom fighter.” For 10 points, name this word that can be defined as the use of violence to instill fear.","formatted_answer":"<b><u>terror<\/b><\/u>ism [or <b><u>terror<\/b><\/u>ist; accept <b><u>Terrorism<\/b><\/u> Risk Insurance Act; accept Comprehensive Convention on International <b><u>Terrorism<\/b><\/u>; accept “one man’s <b><u>terrorist<\/b><\/u> is another man’s freedom fighter”]","answer":"<b><u>terror<\/b><\/u>ism [or <b><u>terror<\/b><\/u>ist; accept <b><u>Terrorism<\/b><\/u> Risk Insurance Act; accept Comprehensive Convention on International <b><u>Terrorism<\/b><\/u>; accept “one man’s <b><u>terrorist<\/b><\/u> is another man’s freedom fighter”]","category":"History","subcategory":"European History","packetNumber":4,"questionNumber":11},{"question":"A paper by Brysbaert and New proposes that norms for this value should be based on SUBTLEX, thus “moving beyond Kučera and Francis.” According to the missing letter effect, people fail to detect target letters more often when this value is high. An effect named for this value can be illustrated by the fact that N400 amplitudes vary inversely with this quantity. The word for this value follows both (*) “term” and “inverse document” in the name of a statistic commonly used in information retrieval. Zipf’s law posits an inverse relationship between this value and rank for words. The Google Ngram Viewer tracks changes in this value for words over time. For 10 points, name this measure of how often a word appears in a corpus.","formatted_answer":"word <b><u>frequency<\/b><\/u>","answer":"word <b><u>frequency<\/b><\/u>","category":"Science","subcategory":"Other Science","packetNumber":4,"questionNumber":12},{"question":"An excerpt titled for this process includes alliterative lists of words like “texture, take, tent, tight, tantalizing, tensing, taste, tendrils, time, tactile, tell me.” A band name that was chosen in order to contribute to this process led to the case Matal v. Tam, in which the Supreme Court found that a provision in the Lanham [LAN-um] Act violated the First Amendment. A section of The Vagina Monologues titled for this process is narrated by a woman who loves the (*) C-word. The use of the phrase “nasty woman” by Hillary Clinton supporters and the use of the word “deplorables” by Trump supporters are examples of this process. For 10 points, name this process in which a pejorative word is rehabilitated by the group targeted by the word.","formatted_answer":"linguistic <b><u>reclamation<\/b><\/u> [or <b><u>reclaim<\/b><\/u>ing words; or <b><u>reappropriation<\/b><\/u>; or <b><u>resignification<\/b><\/u>; prompt on <u>taking back<\/u> words; prompt on <u>rehabilitation<\/u> before “rehabilitated”]","answer":"linguistic <b><u>reclamation<\/b><\/u> [or <b><u>reclaim<\/b><\/u>ing words; or <b><u>reappropriation<\/b><\/u>; or <b><u>resignification<\/b><\/u>; prompt on taking back words; prompt on rehabilitation before “rehabilitated”]","category":"Current Events","subcategory":"Current Events","packetNumber":4,"questionNumber":13},{"question":"A company’s head of marketing coined the name for one of these products by finding the Old High German word for “reward” in Webster’s Dictionary. A name for one of these products, chosen in a magazine naming contest, combines the German words for a big cat and a lizard. One of these products is named for a boat generally considered the smallest class of warship, below a (*) frigate. According to a debunked legend, one of these products sold poorly in Spanish-speaking countries because its name sounds like a Spanish phrase suggesting that it doesn’t work. “Resilient Bullet” and “Mongoose Civique” were among the names proposed by Marianne Moore for one of these products which flopped in the 1950s. For 10 points, name these products that include the Miata and the Edsel.","formatted_answer":"<b><u>car<\/b><\/u>s [or <b><u>auto<\/b><\/u>mobiles; accept other synonyms; prompt on <u>vehicle<\/u>s] (In order, the clues are about the Mazda Miata, the Volkswagen Tiguan, the Chevy Corvette, the Chevy Nova, and the Ford Edsel.)","answer":"<b><u>car<\/b><\/u>s [or <b><u>auto<\/b><\/u>mobiles; accept other synonyms; prompt on vehicles] (In order, the clues are about the Mazda Miata, the Volkswagen Tiguan, the Chevy Corvette, the Chevy Nova, and the Ford Edsel.)","category":"Literature","subcategory":"American Literature","packetNumber":4,"questionNumber":14},{"question":"Westerners traditionally called these things “chops,” a term borrowed from the Hindi chap [chop]. Empress Wu supposedly changed the word for these things to a word meaning “treasure,” because the original word sounded too much like a word for “death.” A script named for these things in English was formalized as the writing system for all of China during the Qin [chin] dynasty. The lost (*) “heirloom” one of these things displays the words “Having received the Mandate of Heaven, live long and prosper.” The zhūwén [zhoo-wen] and báiwén [pie-wen] types of these things have red characters against a white background and vice versa. For 10 points, name these impressions used in place of signatures in China, which use paste or ink rather than the wax impressions used in European countries.","formatted_answer":"<b><u>seal<\/b><\/u>s [or <b><u>xǐ<\/b><\/u>; or <b><u>bǎo<\/b><\/u>; or <b><u>yìn<\/b><\/u>; accept imperial <b><u>seal<\/b><\/u>s; accept <b><u>seal<\/b><\/u> script; accept Heirloom <b><u>Seal<\/b><\/u> of the Realm]","answer":"<b><u>seal<\/b><\/u>s [or <b><u>xǐ<\/b><\/u>; or <b><u>bǎo<\/b><\/u>; or <b><u>yìn<\/b><\/u>; accept imperial <b><u>seal<\/b><\/u>s; accept <b><u>seal<\/b><\/u> script; accept Heirloom <b><u>Seal<\/b><\/u> of the Realm]","category":"Literature","subcategory":"British Literature","packetNumber":4,"questionNumber":15},{"question":"A technique called BIN, which produces clusters that approximate the entities referred to by this word, is used by the web platform BOLD System. The notion of a “historical fate” was incorporated into E. O. Wiley’s definition of this word, which is adapted from George Gaylord Simpson’s definition. A major problem for a popular definition of this word is the existence of (*) “complexes” or “aggregates” which may arise from apomixis [ap-oh-MIX-iss]. The word “concepts” is often used to refer to the dozens of competing definitions of this word, including those based on DNA barcoding and phylogenetics. The standard textbook definition of this word is due to Ernst Mayr [Meyer], who defined it as a reproductively isolated, potentially interbreeding natural population. For 10 points, name this taxonomic level below genus.","formatted_answer":"<b><u>species<\/b><\/u>","answer":"<b><u>species<\/b><\/u>","category":"Science","subcategory":"Biology","packetNumber":4,"questionNumber":16},{"question":"According to a lecture titled “English and Welsh,” words that are similar to this phrase are “extraordinarily frequent” in Welsh. C. S. Lewis pointed out that respelling this phrase as a single word produces “an enchanting proper name.” The teacher Ms. Pomeroy, played by Drew Barrymore, writes this phrase on a chalkboard in Donnie Darko and cites the opinion of a “famous (*) linguist” about this phrase. This phrase can refer to the part of a winery where wine is purchased or sampled. An observation about the phonaesthetic [“phone-aesthetic”] properties of this phrase was popularized by J. R. R. Tolkien, who called this two-word phrase one of the most beautiful in the English language. For 10 points, name this phrase referring to the entrance to an underground storage location.","formatted_answer":"<b><u>cellar door<\/b><\/u>","answer":"<b><u>cellar door<\/b><\/u>","category":"Literature","subcategory":"British Literature","packetNumber":4,"questionNumber":17},{"question":"A lecture that devolves into repetitions of this word is delivered by a historian who is introduced with the caption “A Historian” and who describes “oaken galleys” sailing to England. A Hungarian man repeats this word in a sentence that begins “great boobies, honeybun,” prompting a group of people nearby to repeat this word. This word is repeated in a song parodying Samuel Coleridge-Taylor’s (*) “Viking Song,” performed by a group of Vikings. A café waitress repeats this word ad nauseam in a sketch that inspired the use of this word as well as “ham” and “eggs” as metasyntactic variables in Python. This word is the first part of the portmanteau title of the musical adaptation of Monty Python and the Holy Grail. For 10 points, name this word that now refers to unsolicited email.","formatted_answer":"<b><u>spam<\/b><\/u>","answer":"<b><u>spam<\/b><\/u>","category":"History","subcategory":"European History","packetNumber":4,"questionNumber":18},{"question":"This philosopher argues that the expression “proper name” is improper in a section called “The Battle of Proper Names” which analyzes an incident in which an anthropologist tricked some Nambikwara girls into revealing their names. This philosopher warns that “event” is a “loaded word” at the beginning of an essay about something that has occurred “in the history of the concept of (*) structure.” This author of “Structure, Sign, and Play” used the term “phonocentrism” for the idea that speech is more fundamental than the written word, and coined the term différance [dif-eh-RAHNTS], which is distinguishable from the word différence [dif-eh-RAHNTS] only when written down. For 10 points, name this philosopher whose book Of Grammatology is a seminal text of deconstruction.","formatted_answer":"Jacques <b><u>Derrida<\/b><\/u> [or Jackie Élie <b><u>Derrida<\/b><\/u>]","answer":"Jacques <b><u>Derrida<\/b><\/u> [or Jackie Élie <b><u>Derrida<\/b><\/u>]","category":"Philosophy","subcategory":"Philosophy","packetNumber":4,"questionNumber":19},{"question":"This adjective may derive from the word for a large pea, which in turn is derived from the name of a Spanish village which was alleged to hold the gigantic bones of heroes. A person whose “body is perfectly spherical” wears a hat described by this adjective in a “self-portrait” which begins “how pleasant to know [the author].” This word may ultimately derive from the name of the (*) pass where the battle depicted in The Song of Roland took place. This adjective was invented for a poem which ends with the two title characters dancing “by the light of the moon.” “Mince and slices of quince” are eaten with an object described by this adjective in “The Owl and the Pussycat.” For 10 points, name this nonsense word that Edward Lear used to describe a spoon.","formatted_answer":"<b><u>runcible<\/b><\/u>","answer":"<b><u>runcible<\/b><\/u>","category":"Literature","subcategory":"British Literature","packetNumber":4,"questionNumber":20}],"bonuses":[]}
